<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-11T16:25:49+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">LazyInq</title><subtitle>I love ashutosh Chandra !!</subtitle><author><name>Swastika mukherjee</name></author><entry><title type="html">What they don’t tell you about downshifting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/12/11/what-they-dont-tell-you-about-downshifting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What they don’t tell you about downshifting" /><published>2025-12-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-12-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/12/11/what-they-dont-tell-you-about-downshifting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/12/11/what-they-dont-tell-you-about-downshifting.html"><![CDATA[<p>“Being a downshifter has its ups and downs. It’s great to have free time to yourself but on the other hand you don’t earn much, and this creates a lot of frustration. You can’t afford to go anywhere nice. Not to mention you aren’t getting any recognition from society.”<br />
— <em>Welcome to the Hyunam-Dong Bookshop</em></p>

<p>I had a decent job; comfortable, easy, monotonous. Yet I felt more burnt out than I should have. A tiny little voice in my head urged me to leave it all and the city with it, but my bank account kept me in check. One day, the money just couldn’t make up for the stress of going into work. That’s when I decided to quit. At first, I had a solid plan that would soft launch me back into the same kind of work—with more money. That took an unwelcome detour which left me with no job, not many prospects, and absolutely no desire to return to the hustle.</p>

<p>I found myself packing my bags and heading to the mountains for a hospitality gig that paid even less. Surely, if the pay was less, so would be the work. Living where people vacation sounded like a win. Right? Wrong. I put in more hours, struggled to adjust, and found even less time for myself. The dignity of labour is truly measured by how much “desk” your desk job truly entails. Reality was far removed from my expectations.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1470770841072-f978cf4d019e?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1400&amp;q=80" alt="Quiet mountain road" /></p>

<h2 id="what-i-learnt-from-my-experience">What I learnt from my experience</h2>

<h3 id="cutting-costs-isnt-pleasant">Cutting costs isn’t pleasant</h3>

<p>Only someone who doesn’t worry about money can underestimate how much leverage it brings. It wasn’t just buying fewer things; it was the constant worry I wouldn’t have enough. I started going out less, stopped taking care of myself, and even stopped seeing friends as much.</p>

<h3 id="an-unforeseen-identity-crisis">An unforeseen identity crisis</h3>

<p>For so many of us, work defines who we are. When you meet someone new, “what do you do?” arrives fast. Going from corporate to a small role in hospitality was often met with suspicion and judgment, no matter how well people tried to hide it. We see ourselves through society’s lens—and what people think of us matters.</p>

<h3 id="personal-time-turned-out-to-be-a-myth">Personal time turned out to be a myth</h3>

<p>The whole point of choosing a simpler life was to invest more time in myself. The truth: your habits follow you. Mine were over-pleasing bosses, never saying no, and never feeling like I was doing enough. Even after quitting, I worked just as hard for much less and barely had time to unwind.</p>

<h2 id="so-would-i-recommend-it">So would I recommend it?</h2>

<p>Downshifting has its place. With flexible work and shifting values, more people are hopping in. Many report being happier and more fulfilled. But there are tradeoffs. Here’s what I would do differently:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Have a plan.</strong> Build a small nest egg to get through the first few months comfortably. Uncertainty is built in; cash buys you breathing room.</li>
  <li><strong>Choose an alternate path carefully.</strong> Know what burned you out. Pick work that avoids the same triggers—whether that’s physical, mental, or cultural.</li>
  <li><strong>Test the waters.</strong> Ease into the new life. Try the new hobby or job without over-committing. It’s not about being the best; it’s about checking if it’s best for you.</li>
</ul>

<p>Just have an open mind. You may have exhausted other possibilities. It may work; it may not. You won’t know until you try. It is a risk, but the reward could be peace of mind and a more fulfilling life. Passing over a high-profile career doesn’t mean you’ve given up on hopes, dreams, or goals. It’s a respite to do things on your own timeline, without compromising your wellness.</p>]]></content><author><name>Swastika mukherjee</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving the grind sounds freeing—until the money, identity, and habits you kept from your old job follow you into your “simple” life.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1500530855697-b586d89ba3ee?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1400&amp;q=80" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1500530855697-b586d89ba3ee?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1400&amp;q=80" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Broke but want to travel alone? — Here’s how</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/12/04/broke-but-want-to-travel-alone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Broke but want to travel alone? — Here’s how" /><published>2025-12-04T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-12-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/12/04/broke-but-want-to-travel-alone</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/12/04/broke-but-want-to-travel-alone.html"><![CDATA[<p>“Travelling as a broke college student”, the idea may not be new to friends living overseas, but for someone raised in an Indian middle-class family, it can feel uncanny.</p>

<p>When I told my parents, as a 20-year-old not nearly fresh out of college, that I wanted to roam the streets of India, volunteer at hostels, and meet new people, they only had one thing to say: “but what for?”. Concern for safety aside, the idea of wandering aimlessly, even for a little while, does not sit well with brown parents. But my mind was made up. As I packed my bags and left behind the comfort of home and two upset parents, I was a ball of nerves—and excited.</p>

<p>If, like me, travelling the world is calling out to you but you don’t know where to begin, make this guide your best friend.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1507525428034-b723cf961d3e?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1400&amp;q=80" alt="Sunrise over the ocean" /></p>

<h2 id="why-travel-solo">Why travel solo?</h2>

<p>If you are new to the world of travel, going off on a solo adventure can be intimidating. Planning, logistics, and life’s plain unpredictability can definitely use some company. On the other hand, going solo may open up many otherwise-missed opportunities.</p>

<p>When you travel alone, you live on your own schedule. Making impromptu plans is easier when you don’t have to account for another person. With this flexibility you can make better use of your resources, especially on a budget. Skip the fancy stay and put your money toward trying out an adventure sport or exploring the local cuisine instead.</p>

<p>Aside from the place itself, it’s the people that add the most colour to any trip. Travelling alone gives you a chance to mingle with new people, hear their stories, and sometimes even make friendships that last a lifetime. All this and more can make travelling solo worth your while.</p>

<h2 id="what-could-go-wrong">What could go wrong?</h2>

<p>It’s easy to get enchanted by the idea of being a nomad. But it’s not without its challenges. Be prepared.</p>

<h3 id="money-matters">Money matters</h3>

<p>My new-found freedom came with a very empty pocket. Money can’t buy happiness, but it does buy the essentials (and some much-needed comforts) during travel. Plan your spend on food and transport, but also set aside funds for fun activities and emergencies.</p>

<h3 id="meeting-new-people">Meeting new people</h3>

<p>Even solo travellers need company. Introducing yourself can be daunting, especially if everyone already seems paired off. My mantra: “what’s there to lose?”. The worst they can say is no. Put yourself out there, offer snacks, or chime into the discussion—you might make a new friend.</p>

<h3 id="unforeseen-roadblocks">Unforeseen roadblocks</h3>

<p>Missed a bus, lost a bag, or started feeling sick? It can feel like a disaster, but a backup plan, an emergency contact, and travel insurance go a long way. You can’t plan for everything, so stay calm and keep moving.</p>

<h3 id="safety">Safety</h3>

<p>Safety is the number one concern for solo travellers, especially women. Pick the right stay, share your whereabouts with someone, and travel in groups for hikes or treks. It can literally be a life saver.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-work-around-it">How to work around it</h2>

<p>Preparedness makes the difference. Here are simple ways to stay ahead of the odds and still have fun.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1473181488821-2d23949a045a?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1400&amp;q=80" alt="Budget travel notebook and coffee" /></p>

<h3 id="planning-and-spontaneity">Planning and spontaneity</h3>

<p>Good travel is an equal mix of planning and flexibility. Once you pick a destination, plan your itinerary. Access to medical facilities and good connectivity matter if you are staying longer. I like to look up cafes and hangs—they become regular haunts for travellers and are perfect places to find company.</p>

<h3 id="research-the-locality">Research the locality</h3>

<p>Accustom yourself to local customs and traditions. Some countries dress more modestly. Knowing how to dress, eat, and behave so you don’t come off as rude (or get into trouble) makes your stay more pleasant.</p>

<h3 id="getting-the-best-deals">Getting the best deals</h3>

<p>Extra cash always helps on the road. Book stays and flights 2–3 months in advance for better prices, especially in peak season. Turn on price alerts. If your schedule is flexible, travel off-season. Use comparison sites like Google Flights, Kayak, or Skyscanner. To stretch your budget, consider hostels with shared dorms.</p>

<h3 id="budget-calculator">Budget calculator</h3>

<p>Use a simple budget calculator. List one-time expenses (airfare, transport) and daily expenses (stay, food, entertainment). Break down your total budget and allocate a percentage to each based on local rates. Free online travel budget calculators can split expenses with friends, track savings, and convert currencies.</p>

<h3 id="airfare-hacks">Airfare hacks</h3>

<p>Book one-way tickets to mix airlines and pick the cheapest legs. Flying Monday–Wednesday is often cheaper than weekends. If you have multiple airports nearby, try the smaller ones. Book with a credit card to earn miles and deals. Unbooked seats sometimes get upgraded—ask with confidence.</p>

<h2 id="but-most-importantly">But most importantly…</h2>

<p>When I first stepped out, I over-planned everything. Over time I realised it’s best not to get too caught up in the details once the basics are covered. Listen to your gut, ask for help when you need it, and if you run out of ideas, come back to this guide. You’re there to have fun—and that’s one detail you should never forget. Happy travels!</p>]]></content><author><name>Swastika mukherjee</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Travelling on a student budget can work if you plan, stay flexible, and use a few simple money and safety habits.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1507525428034-b723cf961d3e?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1200&amp;q=80" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1507525428034-b723cf961d3e?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1200&amp;q=80" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>